Guide to the Cornelius Vanderbilt Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Cornelius Vanderbilt Papers
1776-1953
1901-1928
MS 1181
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
(6 boxes)
Chiefly correspondence, memoranda, a notebook, and memorabilia relating to Vanderbilt's service as an officer in the U.S. Engineers during World War I. Also included are technical notebooks on mathematics, chemistry, and engineering (1897-1926). Of particular note are two illustrated manuscript volumes: one by Joseph Lyddell Peyton outlining a course of instruction for British naval officers, and the second by John Burnell showing the headlands of various coastlines in Europe and Africa. Also in the papers are checkbooks, guestbooks, a nurse's record of Vanderbilt's case of typhoid fever (1902-1903), and inventories of the Vanderbilt library in New York City, and of his yacht.
Vanderbilt, Cornelius, 1873-1942
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Cornelius Vanderbilt and the Vanderbilt estate, 1944-1945; and Donald Wing, 1968.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains a miscellany of papers relating to Cornelius Vanderbilt III. There is a small amount of general correspondence dealing mainly with business matters, and a larger selection of military correspondence, memoranda, and a notebook, all stemming from Vanderbilt's service as an officer in the U.S. Engineers during World War I. There are in addition a few items of memorabilia, two inventories, and five photographic copies of commissions issued by the U.S. Continental Congress and other Revolutionary-era bodies.
The remainder of the papers consists of bound volumes, the most interesting of which are two lavishly illustrated manuscripts: A Plan Executed At the Royal Naval Academy, by Joseph Lyddell Peyton (1803); and Martimagraphy or A Discription [sic] of the Sea Coast, by John Burnell (n.d.). The first provides a complete course of instruction for British Naval Officers, while the second contains drawings of headlands of various coastlines. The other volumes in the papers include a nurse's report of Vanderbilt's bout of typhoid in 1902-1903, twenty-three notebooks on topics such as engineering, mathematics, and chemistry, six checkbooks, an engagement book, and four guestbooks.
These papers were donated to Yale University by Mrs. Vanderbilt and the Vanderbilt estate in 1944-1945, and by Donald Wing in 1968.
Biographical / Historical
Cornelius Vanderbilt: capitalist; A.B., Yale, 1895, Ph.B., 1898, M.E., 1899; officer in the U.S. Engineers, 1917-1918.
Chemistry; Coasts; Engineering; Landscape drawing; Libraries -- Inventories; Mathematics; Nautical charts; Navies -- Officers; Navigation; Shipping; Typhoid fever; World War, 1914-1918 -- United States; Yachting; Yachts; New York (State); Soldiers; Burnell, John; Peyton, Joseph Lyddell; Vanderbilt, Cornelius, 1873-1942; Old Royal Naval College Greenwich
- Inventory
  - General correspondence, 1901-1933, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
  - Military correspondence and memoranda, 1912-1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 3 - 9)
  - Notebooks
    - "Notes from Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers", 1880 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Notes III" [re: engineering and mathematics], 1897 September (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Notes IV" and "Notes V" [re: engineering and mathematics], 1898-1899 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "North Star" [Yacht], I and II, 1903-1904 August (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "North Star" III, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Paper Technology", 1910 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Patent References", 1910 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "Cellulose", 1910 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Mathematics and engineering, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "Chemistry Experiments", 1910 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "Chemistry Experiments" IV and V, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Chemistry, 1913, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - World War I, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "Calculus" I and II, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "Calculus III", undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Two miscellaneous notebooks, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Poetry, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Checkbooks, 1900-1906, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 21 - 23)
  - Engagement book, 1926-1928 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Guestbooks, 1943-1953 (Box 4, Folder 25 - 28)
  - Memorabilia, 1900-1919, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Inventory of books, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Inventory of N.Y. Atlantic [yacht], undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Martimagraphy or a Discription [sic] of Sea Coasts..., by John Burnell, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - "Report on the Green Gobbler Mine," by C.E. Julihn, 1908 February 19 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - A Plan Executed at the Royal Naval Academy, by Joseph Lyddell Pey, 1800-1803 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - "Typhoid Fever, 1902-1903," nurse's record, 1902 December- 1903 July (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Photographic copies of commissions from U.S. Continental Congress and other bodies, 1776-1797 (Box 6, Folder 36)